ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with ~8 years of proven success delivering on Objectives and Key business Results. Established and scaled enterprise—level Digital Transformation initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Enabled Data Science's 65% overall AI/ML market share across business functions within British Petroleum's US onshore O&G division and independently produced \$997MM in value. Delivered patent—pending AI—powered computational chemistry solutions — valued at \$500M+ annually — for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

- · Directed and executed Data Science & ML Engineering Digital Transformation strategy achieving a 45% AI/ML market share in Exploration & Development and enabling the team's 65% AI/ML market share across the organization.
- · Successfully delivered 88% of the planned Q2 features in Data Science and ML Engineering within the project scope.
- · Managed and productionalized the Long-term Production Risk Assessment app via Streamlit for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the Azure cloud to AWS cloud Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index report migration.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- Generated \$977MM in the Bone Spring formation with a well development plan NPV of \$700MM, Drilling & Completions cost reductions of \$250MM, and core collection avoidance amounting to \$27MM launching AI Lithofacies Prediction in SLB Techlog, enabling regional fluid mobility assessments, and facilitating well development prioritization.
- · Drove \$20MM in annual value for Reservoir Engineering's EOR program productionalizing the ML Refracturing Model with Streamlit and inducing a 500% efficiency gain in the stakeholders' well prospecting & assurance workflows.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed the **patent-pending** Automated Sensor Calibration program driving a forecasted \$500M+ in annual cost reductions and **provisioning Neural Processing Units** for next-generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Led cross—functional efforts producing a **21% enhancement** to Mass Spec signal fidelity (SciPy.optimize/Statsmodels), designed A/B Quality Control tests (SciPy.stats/Nolds) for all Mass Spec sensors, and documented proprietary algorithms.
- · Established KPIs and executed A/B simulation tests, generating synthetic GC–MS data using PySwarms and SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate attaining 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems.
- · Invented the Bijective Neural Architecture for density estimation via PyTorch yielding a 95% increase in model accuracy.

Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Data Lab

June 2017 – August 2017 Syracuse, New York

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

Technology Analyst

 $June\ 2016-August\ 2016$

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

Self-employed

June 2015 – September 2015 Syracuse, New York

· Engineered information retrieval systems for **British Petroleum** and local government clients as a subcontractor.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

August 2014 – May 2015 Syracuse, New York

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors February 2024 USPTO Application 18/686,753 Patent Pending INVITED PRESENTATIONS Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing July 2024 BP Geophysics R&D Seminar Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches April 2018 Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT April 2024/December 2023 Core Analysis Workshop UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX April 2023 Havens Consulting Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics June 2019 Dr. S. Joe Qin, President of Lingnan University **HONORS & AWARDS** Graduate Merit Scholarship August 2017 - May 2018 Syracuse University Summa Cum Laude May 2017 Syracuse University The Warren Semon Prize May 2017 Syracuse University Dean's Leadership Grant September 2014 Syracuse University Dean's List August 2014 - May 2017 Syracuse University

The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 - May 2017

Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University May 2017

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Agile Project Management, OKRs, CRISP-DM Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling, Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy, NLTK,

Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog